<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>655</fr:anchor><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:addr>Lan1959</fr:addr><fr:route>Lan1959.xml</fr:route><fr:title>Abelian varieties</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>1959</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>S. Lang</fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue">Interscience Publishers</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex">@book{Lan1959,
  title = {Abelian varieties},
  author = {Lang, S.},
  year = {1959},
  publisher = {Interscience Publishers},
}</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:contributions></fr:contributions><fr:context></fr:context><fr:related></fr:related><fr:backlinks><fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>654</fr:anchor><fr:taxon>Remark</fr:taxon><fr:addr>fga3.v-5-remark-5.3</fr:addr><fr:route>fga3.v-5-remark-5.3.xml</fr:route><fr:number>5.3</fr:number><fr:parent>fga3.v-5</fr:parent></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>
    Note that the proof given here uses neither the preliminary construction of Jacobians of curves or families of curves nor the theory of abelian varieties or abelian schemes, and in this way it essentially distinguishes itself from traditional treatments, such as those in the book by Lang <fr:link
href="Lan1959.xml"
type="local"
addr="Lan1959">[Lan1959]</fr:link> or the article by Chevalley <fr:link
href="Che1960.xml"
type="local"
addr="Che1960">[Che1960]</fr:link>, which follow the path sketched by Weil.
    Even in the case of Jacobians of non-singular curves over an algebraically closed field (the complex numbers, say), the construction given here for the Jacobian is the only one known that comes with the very strong properties that we took as definition in <fr:ref
addr="fga3.v-1"
href="fga3.v-1.xml"
number="1"></fr:ref> (essentially those of Chevalley, but taking into account the "variety of parameters" with nilpotent elements).
    The fact that the construction of Picard schemes should precede, not follow, the theory of abelian varieties is clear a priori, by the fact that, in general, Picard schemes are not, nor do they reduce to, abelian schemes, as we already see in the case of singular curves over an algebraically closed field, where we find the "generalised Jacobians" of Rosenlicht, which are not abelian varieties.
    Furthermore, the theory of abelian varieties, and more generally of abelian schemes, becomes much simpler once we have a theory of Picard schemes in general.
    In particular, the theory of duality for abelian schemes, and notably the results of Cartier type, then become slightly more formal (cf. for example [Mumford–Tate seminar, 1962]).
  </fr:p></fr:mainmatter></fr:tree></fr:backlinks><fr:references></fr:references></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>