<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>268</fr:anchor><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:addr>Mum1961</fr:addr><fr:route>Mum1961.xml</fr:route><fr:title>An elementary theorem in geometric invariant theory</fr:title><fr:date><fr:year>1961</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author>D. Mumford</fr:author></fr:authors><fr:meta
name="venue"><fr:em>Bull. Amer. Math. Soc.</fr:em> <fr:strong>67</fr:strong> pp. 483–486</fr:meta><fr:meta
name="bibtex">@article{Mum1961,
  title = {An elementary theorem in geometric invariant theory},
  author = {Mumford, D.},
  year = {1961},
  journal = {Bull. Amer. Math. Soc.},
  volume = {67},
  pages = {483--486},
}</fr:meta></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:contributions></fr:contributions><fr:context></fr:context><fr:related></fr:related><fr:backlinks><fr:tree
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>267</fr:anchor><fr:taxon>Remarks</fr:taxon><fr:addr>fga3.v-5-remarks-5.2</fr:addr><fr:route>fga3.v-5-remarks-5.2.xml</fr:route><fr:number>5.2</fr:number><fr:parent>fga3.v-5</fr:parent></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>
    It is not out of the question that <fr:tex>\underline { \operatorname {Pic} } _{X/S}</fr:tex> exist whenever <fr:tex>f \colon  X \to  S</fr:tex> is proper and flat and such that the homomorphisms <fr:tex>k(s) \to \operatorname {H} ^0(X_s, \mathcal {O} _{X_s})</fr:tex> (for <fr:tex>s \in  S</fr:tex>) are isomorphisms (this latter condition also then implying that <fr:tex>\mathcal {O} _S \xrightarrow { \sim }  f_*( \mathcal {O} _X)</fr:tex>, and that this remain true after any base change <fr:tex>S' \to  S</fr:tex>).
    This at least is what we can prove in the setting of analytic spaces, if <fr:tex>f</fr:tex> is further assumed to be projective, by a differential method (that of Chow, if I am not mistaken) explained in [<fr:link
href="Gro1960a.xml"
type="local"
addr="Gro1960a">Gro1960a</fr:link>, IX, 3.1].
    
    In this method, the passage to the quotient by a <fr:em>proper</fr:em> and flat equivalence relation in an open of the scheme of divisors is replaced by the passage to the quotient by the projective group in the scheme of immersions of <fr:tex>X</fr:tex> into <fr:tex>\mathbb {P}_S^r</fr:tex>.
    This method can probably be adapted to the case of schemes, using the results of Mumford on the passage to the quotient by the projective group <fr:link
href="Mum1961.xml"
type="local"
addr="Mum1961">[Mum1961]</fr:link>;
    for now, there is no written proof, except when <fr:tex>X</fr:tex> has "lots of local sections" over <fr:tex>S</fr:tex>, for example if <fr:tex>X</fr:tex> is separable over a complete local ring with algebraically closed residue field.
    In principle, the method in question is of more general scope, since it also gives the existence of Picard preschemes in the case where these are not separated, and where the first method thus necessarily fails.
    (Technically, the difficulty comes from the fact that, when the geometric fibres of <fr:tex>f</fr:tex> are not integral, then the functor envisaged in <fr:ref
addr="fga3.v-4-theorem-4.3"
href="fga3.v-4-theorem-4.3.xml"
taxon="Theorem"
number="4.3"></fr:ref> is no longer representable by the projective bundle <fr:tex>\mathbb {P}( \mathscr { Q } )</fr:tex> itself, but by an <fr:em>open</fr:em> of this, which leads to the delicate question of the passage to the quotient by an equivalence relation that is flat but not proper).
  </fr:p><fr:p><fr:em>[Comp.]</fr:em>
    As I point out at the start of the next talk, the existence conjecture suggested here is false, but Mumford has proven a slightly weaker theorem using his methods.
  </fr:p></fr:mainmatter></fr:tree></fr:backlinks><fr:references></fr:references></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>